Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 5 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 December-1780 December Mss.B.F85inventory05
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Cuming, James. L'Orient
    Arrival of two vessels from America; the public despatches were sent from Brest, and the duplicates under the care of a M. de Mattey. If Franklin will oblige him with freight, he can give the vessels such despatch as may encourage his friends in America to carry on a more constant trade with France than they have hitherto attempted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Concerning the choice of Governor for Massachusetts; Mr. Hancock has a great majority of votes; elements in his favor. Arrival of the "Alliance" with Dr. [Arthur] Lee on board; Landais either relinquished his command during the voyage of else it was wrested from him; a Court of Inquiry sitting upon the matter; Dr. Lee's evidence points to the Captain's insanity; officers and men complain loudly of being kept out of their prize-money; people of discretion will wait quietly for accounts from France. Arrival of Chevalier de Ternay at Rhode Island, followed soon after by much stronger British fleet; their hopes, therefore, of striking an important blow are very small. A feigned attack on Newport caused the Massachusetts militia to fly to the aid of the French; favorable impression created by such promptitude. Washington's army reinforced. The necessity of getting the British off the Continent. Caricatures received; striking example of barbarity; will dispose of them so as to do good. Acknowledging Franklin's kindness to his grandson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Read, Thomas. L'Orient
    Announcing his arrival from Philadelphia, having obtained leave from Congress to make the voyage. Admiral Ternay and his fleet had arrived at Rhode Island and Admiral Graves had left New York with eight sail of the line, his destination being unknown. Expects to return the end of the month; will be happy to execute any commands, both public and private.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Sturler, Baron. Paris
    Explaining that he lent M. De Freÿ the twenty louis to reclaim the notes in Franklin's hands, which he now forwards; hopes the sum may be returned him; his reasons for lending it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 9; L.S. 3p.; Francy, Jean-Baptiste-Lazare Théveneau de. Bordeaux
    Concerning an order for a certain quantity of tobacco to be delivered in ten days to M. [Pierre François] Chevallié.
    (Copy. In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 9; L. 18p.; Ruston, Thomas. London
    The defects in the money system of the United States and how they can be remedied. Public credit, how it is maintained and how it can be impaired. The financial condition of the principal nations of Europe. Recommends the establishment in the United States of a central banking institution somewhat similar to the Bank of England or the Bank of Amsterdam, but having a freer scope for its operations.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Frey, Joseph-Pierre-Charles, baron de. Paris
    Is in despair at being forced to ask again for the twenty louis, but has waited in vain for remittances from his father.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Dusaulx, Jean. Paris
    Has the honor of sending the letter which asks for news of M. Michaelis's son.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Belcamp
    Introducing Mr. John Collins, of Dublin, who will explain his business. Their Parliament began with spirit, but at the close of the last session forfeited every title to virtue and honor. The four Americans mentioned in his last letter, have been released without any expense; supposes they paid their respects to Franklin on their way to Bordeaux.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 11; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Searle, James. Paris
    Sends two packets and seven letters from America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Baudin, Augustin. Saint-Martin-de-Ré
    His intention of settling in Pennsylvania with a small amount of capital; captured twice by the enemy and thrown into prison; asks that Franklin will reimburse him for the amount of money he lost.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Woodmason, James. London
    The three machines for making copies of writings are ready to be delivered.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Expected arrival of the King of Sweden. Well-content with the manner in which the incendiary, Knyphausen, has been received in New Jersey.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Potts, Samuel. Paris
    Inviting Dr. Franklin and his grandson to dine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Duplessÿ, L Gourlet. Noyon
    Begging for an answer to his petition sent to Franklin together with his invalid's certificate and the certificate of his services to Congress; is a cripple and will have nothing till the death of his mother, who is old and feeble.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 On or After Sept. 17; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Leray de, 1725-1803
    Enclosing a letter [3 p., in French] from his friend, de Monplaisir, which proves that Jones is little fitted to promote friendly feelings between the Americans and the French. The packets confided by Franklin to his care and sent on board the "Corvette," were thrown into the sea; the "Corvette" has returned and will wait for others.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Arrival of the "Mercury," Capt. Samson, fitted out by the Massachusetts State to carry over the stores which Mr. Austin was to have provided; Capt. Samson's capture of a Portuguese vessel. Great expectations in America of a second division to reinforce M. de Ternay; afraid the Ministry has forgotten all about it. Almost all the clothing ready to be shipped.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Castries, Fleury. Paris
    Hears that news has been received of the arrival of Messrs. de Ternay and Rochambeau at Rhode Island; as her son is serving in that squadron, she is most eager to learn anything concerning those gentlemen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 14; L.S. 1p.; Conkling, Joseph. Isle de Ré
    Hoped his brig the "Whim" and her cargo would be soon delivered; the long delay very bad for the tobacco; begs Franklin to use his influence on his behalf, as he fears he will hardly make enough out of his cargo to pay the charges.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Wilt and Delmestre. Nantes
    Forwarded to Franklin a bill of exchange almost a month before; asking that, for the future, the bills may be accepted as soon as they come to hand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Confidence in English funds beginning to weaken. Public opinion recovering from the false notions caused by the capture of Charles-town.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 After September 16]; A.N. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Leray de, 1725-1803
    Requesting Franklin to send him the order for ordnance to be purchased at Bordeaux.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Assarts, Louis-Germain Dupin d'. Assarts near Nevers
    Offers his services to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Desiring information concerning Mr. Searle who, report says, conies to Holland as a representative of the Unites States; expressing his own uneasiness and apprehension concerning his future.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 18; A.L.S. 5p.; Mazurié, Jh. Laderneau
    Complaining that the American ships are not allowed to load or unload at Landerneau, a port far better suited than Brest to all affairs of commerce; begs Franklin to use his influence to obtain for this port certain advantages.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1780 September 18; A.L.S. Fra[nci]s Hopkinson. 1p.; The Treasurer of Loans
    Notification of the issuance of bills of exchange pursuant to the Resolution of Congress of September 1.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Gordon, Alexander. Paris
    Enclosing letters to be forwarded to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Turini, Pierre. Venice
    New work on the method of erecting conductors of lightning.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 424).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Bassi, Anton-Benedetto. Paris
    Concerning a subscription for his new work on Italian poetry.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 18; A.L.S. 1p.; John de Neufville and Son. Antwerp
    Waited for a favorable opportunity to forward the portrait on china, of the great General Washington. Always glad to be of service to the American cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Has given notice respecting the shipment of the fifty-seven pieces of cannon belonging to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Articles printed in the newspapers to give a just idea of American affairs; their success.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Dalgres, -----. Paris
    Sending several bills of exchange for acceptance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Bassi, Anton-Benedetto. Paris
    Is the author of the pamphlet entitled "Observations on the Italian Poets"; sent Franklin, the day before, a letter concerning subscriptions for a new work now in press; begs the favor of a reply.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Hodgson, William. London
    The Commissioners admit having received the men specified by the certificates; fifty-two prisoners still due to England. Case of Capt. Robert Scott, of the privateer "Golden Eagle," who was allowed to return to England on parole; willing to reckon him as if he came in a cartel. Enclosing a list of prisoners taken by American cruisers and confined at St. Omer's; the Board of Sick and Hurt desires their discharge which they will allow in account.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Pommereuille, -----, sieur de. Paris
    Desires a military appointment; has already served in the United States as a protégé of la Fayette; desires only his passage and letters of recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Mr. Searle's mission. Curious to hear what is passing in Ireland; their attitude towards England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 22; L. 3p.; Petrie, Samuel. London
    Unforeseen circumstances will detain longer than he intended when he left Paris. The elections in England, and their venality. When he landed in England Parliament had just been dissolved so he posted down to a borough in the West where he was received with open arms and announced his candidature, but was defeated by a corrupt manoeuvre on the evening preceding the election. The results of the elections.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Juvel Neveux and Cauchoit. Rouen
    Wish to know where bills on Franklin are honored.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 22; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Allen, ------. Paris
    Will dine with Dr. Franklin on Sunday next.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 22; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Thaxter, John Jr. Paris
    Will dine with Dr. Franklin on sunday next.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Scott, George. Naples
    Has received, by the last post, a letter from their worthy friend Dr. P[riestley], who desired that his parting from Lord Shelburne and his present situation might be imparted to Dr. Franklin; however, as he expects to return by sea, encloses an exact copy of said letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 23; L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Ariel," at sea
    Received Franklin's letter, orders and public despatches by the Comte de Vauban; explains his proceedings with respect to the men who served in the privateer, "Madame." Concerning the expense of the "Ariel"; acted for the best from the beginning. Has done with Chaumont; bore his base conduct too long, but has now sent to Versailles such proofs as will, he hopes, prevent his doing further mischief. Distributed the money entrusted to him according to orders. No man loves, esteems and venerates Franklin with a more honest and grateful heart that he does.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 23; A.L.S. 2p.; J.F. Frin and Co. Paris
    Concerning certain bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 25; A.L.S. 3p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Their acceptance of some new draughts on Mr. Laurens. In receipt of remittances from John Leverer, passenger on board a vessel to their consignment; suppose she has been lost. Very desirous of news from America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 25; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Dillon, Comtesse. Paris
    Thanking him for forwarding her letters and sending another one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing a copy of his memoir [2 p.] on American commerce, which he intends presenting to the Swedish and Russian Ministers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 26; D.S. Cha[rle]s Lee, Sec[retar]y, 2p.; The Board of Treasury
    Orders carrying out the Resolutions of Congress of August 23d and 30th relative to the issuance of bills to the amount of $150,000 and $29,105.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 26; L.S. 2p.; Lambert, Sir John. Paris
    Begging the acceptance of certain bills of exchange, which had not the proper endorsement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 27; A.L.S. 1p.; David, ------, l’aîné. Morlaix
    During his last visit to Passy, Dr. Franklin promised him the position of Consul at the port of Morlaix, as soon as the necessary instructions arrived from Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Juvel Neveux and Cauchoit. Rouen
    Begging that the enclosed bill may be honored.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Cellins, Thomas
    Fearful that his son's name, instead of his own, was inserted by his friend Sir Edward Newenham, through some mistake.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Blanchard, Joseph
    Applies for reparation for injury to his character by Messrs. Taylor and Trambell.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Ruston, Thomas. London
    The most profound secrecy respecting the dispatches brought by General Dalrymple, who left New York in the beginning of September. The friends of the Ministry acknowledge the news he brings is very bad. That they were in consternation at New York as the result of de Temay's arrival in Rhode Island; measures taken to meet him. It is reported that Cornwallis is Burgoyned in Carolina; further reinforcements expected from France. Quebec fleet taken and carried into New England. Two prevailing opinions regarding the outcome of the war. Asks him about the financial condition of the country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Poteins, —, chevalier de. Rabastens
    Money belonging to him in America; begs for information as to the best means of obtaining the equivalent in French money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Poliange, Mlle — de. Paris
    Franklin's promise in regard to her relative captured by the English in 1778.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 Septenber 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Bertrand, -----. Paris
    Asking about a Mr. Joseph Redmond, of Ireland, who has resided in Philadelphia for over forty years.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Account of the King of Sweden's visit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 Oct. 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Desegray, Beaugéard Fils and Cie. St Malo
    Mr. Williams has again ordered a quantity of saltpetre for an American vessel at l'Orient.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Recommending Mr. Samuel Andrews; his business concerns the capture of a Dutch vessel by the French. He sent his books, trunks and clothes to Franklin's house; if this proves inconvenient, he will have them stored. Obliged to remain at Amsterdam until Mr. Laurens arrives. Asks for a copy of Franklin's much-talked of letter to the Grand Pensionary of Holland. What the Dutch Republic will do in the Northern Confederation is a question which divides all parties.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Gregorie, David. Dunkirk
    The subjoined vouchers prove the abuse made by Capt. Macatter, of the "Black Princess," of the power-vested in him by the United States; statement made by the master of the brig "John," that, having been captured by the "Black Princess," one of her officers compelled him to sign a ransom bill for £400 sterling, though the cargo was not worth half that sum; ineffectual efforts he has made towards adjustment and compromise; begs Franklin to use his authority in the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780.] September 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Woulfe, George
    Sending a letter which M.S. Petrie desired should be delivered into Dr. Franklin's own hands.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Capt. De Freÿ. Todi
    Begs for information concerning his brother.
    (In French).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Lebègue de Presle, Achille-Guillaume. Châtillon
    Concerning the latest trick which Mr. B[enjamin] Wilson exhibited at the Court of London; advisability of undeceiving the French Physicians in regard to the assertions made by Mr. Wilson; suggests quoting what took place in London and confirming the usefulness of pointed conductors. Encloses a letter to be forwarded to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Richelot, Capt. Rennes
    In the service of Congress, sent to France in the cartel ship after the capture of Charlestown; has some American notes; desires information to enable him to secure their equivalent in French money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Paradise, John. Paris
    Requesting Dr. Franklin's company at dinner together with other American gentlemen, on the day when he shall become a complete member of the American republic.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Courter, Harmon. L'Orient
    Delivered the despatches entrusted to him to Congress. In spite of Franklin, Deane and Lee's joint letter of recommendation, met with a cool reception; thinks this was due to Mr. Lee and his friends. Is now in l'Orient with the ship "Jay" which he will have to sell if he cannot get a full freight back to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 2; L.S. 1p.; Ceronia, Joseph. Genoa
    Has sent his second son to Philadelphia under the care of Mr. Morris; has still two left whom he intends to dedicate to the service of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Bernard de Chasteauvieux, — de. Namur
    His son to raise a regiment and embark with it to America, the clothing, arms and traveling expenses to be provided by the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Chaumont, Le Ray de, fille ainée. Passy
    Concerning bills for horses and carriages hired by Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 2; A.L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Rectifying a mistake in the bills.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 3; L.S. 1p.; de Puchelle, -------. Paris
    Enclosing a letter from the wife of M. de Flad, who is in America with the Comte de Rochambeau, to be forwarded.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Denmark's attitude on the question of armed neutrality. Arrival of a Russian courier with the agreement drawn up; reasons why Holland must agree to an armed neutrality; other nations likely to join. The King of Sweden's coolness towards the English; addition to his memoir for the Russian and Swedish Ministers [1p.].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 4; N. in 3d P. 1p.; de Leempoel, Professor. Paris
    Thanking Dr. Franklin for his courtesies to him and regrets he is obliged to leave immediately for Louvain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 4; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Mr. and Mrs. Hartley and Mr. Batley. Paris
    Accepting his invitation for the following Friday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Off Groix
    Has at last the prospect of leaving, as Commodore Jones has everything on board and a favorable wind is springing up. Three ships to sail for America under convoy of the "Ariel." No news except the arrest of Capt. Landais by order of Congress, and the account of the glorious spirit prevailing throughout the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Branco, -------. Brou
    The decree respecting the "Queen of Portugal"; will pay his respects to Franklin as soon as he receives the papers concerning the prize by the American corsair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Douillemond, -------. Menin
    Offers the services of an officer who has served in the police force; his travelling expenses and his passage to America are all he asks for.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 9; A.L.S. 4p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Naval superiority of the enemy all along the coast; arrival of French fleet has served as a check on Sir Harry Clinton and has raised the States to spirited, through temporary, measures, which have enabled the army to offer battle upon equal terms; American naval superiority of the greatest importance; with that, they could accomplish something. No intelligence about the clothing; shocking situation the army is in; the men almost naked; no arms or powder; begs for fifteen or twenty thousand complete suits exclusive of those expected. Gen. Gates's account of the battle of Camden incorrect; the militia ran but the Continental troops behaved to perfection. Patriotic plan to be adopted by the Eastern States which will insure independence. Franklin will hear of Arnold's trickery and André's execution.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Dana, Francis M. Antwerp
    The enclosed bills are the property of Mr. Jonathan L. Austin; will commit them to the care of Mr. Samuel Bradford who will present them for acceptance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Begs that Franklin will order the vessel, the "Marquis de la Fayette," to be loaded with all the ammunition she can carry, for the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Conkling, Joseph. Isle de Ré
    The bearer is an officer with him on the brig "Whim"; begs Franklin to assist him in obtaining an order from the Admiralty to deliver his cargo, guns and effects.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 9; A.L.S. 3p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Has just received news of Mr. Laurens being taken and carried to Dartmouth; regard this as a greater misfortune than the loss of the tobacco sent by Congress, which was also taken; Mr. Laurens's papers thrown overboard but were unfortunately recovered before much damage was done them; his son is in London and will see Mr. Laurens, if it is possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Adams, James. "Mill Prison," Plymouth